Anbuvenkatesh A

Senior Software Engineer

Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India | +91-9944183012 | anbuvenkatesh.a@outlook.com



Profile

- 9.5 years of experience in architecting and building high performant distributed systems across various cloud platforms and on edge servers across banking, ecommerce, and satellite network domain.
- Strategically applying LLMs to develop sophisticated RAG and Agentic systems, optimizing information retrieval and autonomous task execution.
- Led engineering initiatives, encompassing hiring and training, alongside comprehensive project planning, execution and management.

Management Skills

Hiring, Mentoring, PI Planning, Project Management and Execution, Scrum, Agile.

Technical Skills

Design Patterns: Microservices, DDD, SOLID, REST, Event-driven, Serverless Architecture.

Programming Languages: Java, Python and Go

Deployment: Docker, K8s, AWS ECS, Lambda, Fargate, SNS, SQS, API Gateway, S3, Secret Manager, Cloud

Watch, Event Bridge, CloudFormation.

Databases: MySQL, Postgres, DynamoDB

CICD: Jenkins, GHA

Al: RAG, Lang Chain, Pinecone.

Experience

VIASAT India Private Limited [Apr 2022 - Present]

- Senior Software Engineer II
 - Involved in hiring and training engineers; planning, execution and managing engineering projects.
 - Involved in architecting services (HLD and LLD) and profiling of various languages and frameworks for edge devices and microservices in the ground, aligning with the overall strategy of the organisation.
 - Architecture and development of secret management microservice, eliminating the production downtime caused by expired certificates and modular software update and delivery for the edge server (Over the Air deployment).
 - Harmonization and development of a common software stack for connectivity platform, that enables internet connectivity via satellite.
 - Building agents for onboarding TLS certificates and status retrieval by creating MCP servers and using langehain for workflows.

Trimble Information Technologies India Private Limited [Mar 2021 – Apr 2022]

- Software Engineer (P2)
 - ❖ Involved in the development of reactive microservices for entitlement management system using vert.x and RxJava which helped in serving millions of requests per day at optimal resource usage / cost.
 - Automated the build and deployment of microservices using Jenkins, CloudFormation and AWS CLI.
 - Contributed to the digital transformation journey by developing cloud native microservices.



Temenos India Private Limited [Jan 2016 - Feb 2021]

- Senior Software Engineer
 - ❖ Involved in the development of microservices for enhancing digital banking to the customers which helped in onboarding the customer in less than 2 minutes and development of loan simulation service with each simulation in less than 500ms.
 - ❖ Had exposure on developing high-performance distributed cloud Native system (AWS and Azure Serverless deployment with Lambdas and Azure Functions) and on-premise deployment using Docker and J2EE, based on both NoSQL (Mongo, and Dynamo DB) and SQL (MySQL) database. Used REST and event driven approach (Kafka and Kinesis) to develop the microservices in different stacks.
 - Analysed and fixed issues, that causes financial impact during high volume transaction processing.
 - ❖ Involved in onsite critical client [Chaabi Bank, Commercial International Bank, Swazi Bank, NBS Bank] upgrades and supported for go-live and post go-live issues.

Education

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.) [2011 – 2015]

Electronics and Communications Engineering – First Class (8.2 CGPA)

Park College of Engineering and Technology, Coimbatore. (Affiliated to Anna University, Chennai)

Higher Secondary [2009 – 2011]

Physics, Chemistry, Maths, Computer Science – Distinction (94%) Saratha Higher Secondary School, Gobichettipalayam, Erode.

Certifications

- Hacker Rank Java / Python
- Building RAG Apps Using MongoDB
- Fundamentals of MCP Hugging Face
- M001: MongoDB Basics
- Databricks Generative Al Associate Certification Preparing

Rewards and Recognition

Secured 3rd Place in Viasat Hackathon'22 [Dec 2022 - Viasat]

Won Third Prize in Viasat Hackathon'22 for creating a slack bot that manages the developer ec2 instances more effectively and thus reducing the AWS costs associated with running the instances without losing productivity.

Viasat Stars – One Team [Aug 2022 - Viasat]

You guys rock as a team! Amongst all the other high priorities and ambiguity, you worked as a team and completed the integration of three major 3rd party dockers. Can't thank you enough. It is critical that our biggest customer believes we can deliver as promised, let alone ahead of time. In addition to everything, you took on the Azul-Teledyne troubleshooting challenge and helped solve that as well. Thank you!

Trimble Bravo [Jul 2021 - Trimble]

For taking complete responsibility and ownership in integration of entitlement system with event services.

Trimble Values: #inspire, #engage and #achieve.

Thank you for taking up responsibility in EMS Events service integration. I see that you have written good code and have thought of the process from top to bottom. Please keep up the good work.

GEM (Going Extra Mile) Award [Jul 2020 - Temenos]

TENACITY - Is an innovator and pioneer who disrupts the status quo; Is driven and hates to lose, so he/she never gives up; Puts Temenos first to achieve great things.

Played crucial role in the development of Origination micro services. Never gives up or compromises with the quality of the product. A positive attitude towards all the changes that comes by his way and does not cherry pick the tasks and motivates team to do so. Lending hands to the team when they need and boosting them to stick to timelines.

HEP'13 - Attempt to Guinness records Event [Jul 2013]

A largest gathering by college students at Coimbatore, for creating awareness against Hepatitis B virus.

Publications

"An efficient retinal art for blind people" - <u>IEEE Podhigai</u>

The aim of this project is to make the visually impaired people to feel the sense of vision by creating a low-cost device. The device uses a specialized software where the adjustments in the images captured from the webcam are made and is then sent to the viewer array placed on the tongue. The signals in the viewer array are coupled to the tongue by which visually impaired person can have a real time access to the external environment.

Personal Details

Date of Birth - 24-March-1994

Languages - English (Professional Working) & Tamil (Native)